<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Docker on Jason&#39;s Google Code-in Blog</title>
    <link>http://codethejason.github.io/blog/tags/docker/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Docker on Jason&#39;s Google Code-in Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 17:16:25 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://codethejason.github.io/blog/tags/docker/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Docker</title>
      <link>http://codethejason.github.io/blog/docker/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 17:16:25 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://codethejason.github.io/blog/docker/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have always seen Docker being talked about in the Linux community and have seen it as one of the DigitalOcean quick app install options. I had no idea what it was and did not realize it&amp;rsquo;s function. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/what-docker&#34;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; is actually a container technology designed to improve efficiency. Traditional virtual machines house their own guest operating system and libraries to run an application. As one can see, if there is a large number of virtual machines running their own operating system, the workflow is inefficient. Docker combines the operating systems and other shared parts, so a low spec server could be running hundreds of containers without a hitch. Docker also makes collaboration and publishing easier since it creates a common framework for people to work together and scales easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Docker has a few tools in its Toolbox to help with development. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/docker-compose&#34;&gt;Docker Compose&lt;/a&gt; is a tool used for running small parts of application on different containers while treating it as a single application. There is no need to manage each and every separate container. &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.docker.com/machine/&#34;&gt;Docker Machine&lt;/a&gt; makes host creation easier by automatically configuring Docker on the hosts. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/docker-swarm&#34;&gt;Docker Swarm&lt;/a&gt; is exactly what it sounds like; it provides clustering capabilities to manage a whole swarm of Docker Engines in a since Docker Engine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.docker.com/engine/installation/&#34;&gt;installation&lt;/a&gt; to be a little bit frustrating because I could not get Docker to work on one of my Windows computers. When I tried to ask for help, there was virtually nobody active on the IRC. I proceeded to install Docker on another computer without a problem. I made a 3rd tier application (talks to database) that connects to MySQL &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/codethejason/gcismallprojects2015/tree/master/simpleDockerApp&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and ran it on a Docker container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, Happy New Year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-dZ7-CqEkHhU/VJ6dGmIHCHI/AAAAAAAAH28/eYAWdPY_XM0/w350/Happy-New-Year.png&#34; alt=&#34;hny&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>