<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pharo on Jason&#39;s Google Code-in Blog</title>
    <link>http://codethejason.github.io/blog/tags/pharo/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pharo on Jason&#39;s Google Code-in Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 01:03:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://codethejason.github.io/blog/tags/pharo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Further Extend a User Management Application in Pharo</title>
      <link>http://codethejason.github.io/blog/pharousermanagementpt2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2016 01:03:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://codethejason.github.io/blog/pharousermanagementpt2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My task was to add a few more fields to the existing ConstantManager package and implement some type of checking mechanism to ensure the password fields match. I accomplished this by adding the instance variables and adding a few methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://puu.sh/mwja3/6cb60041a4.png&#34; alt=&#34;screenshot&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I added a small check using if statements to check that the two passwords match. If the passwords do not match, an alert generated by &lt;code&gt;UIManager&lt;/code&gt; pops up to warn the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://puu.sh/mwjxG/55f91bae81.png&#34; alt=&#34;screenshot&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this task, I would like to modify the code so an additional confirmPassword entry does not have to be created in the Contact database. Also, I would like to implement eMBee&amp;rsquo;s suggestions of hiding the password (best solution found so far is &lt;em&gt;PasswordDialogBox&lt;/em&gt;, but I would prefer it to be in the same form as the other fields) and making the role field into a list of strings instead of one long string with different roles. I am excited to continue working with Pharo smalltalk and will be taking on some more challenges!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extend a User Management Application in Pharo</title>
      <link>http://codethejason.github.io/blog/pharousermanagement/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 10:02:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://codethejason.github.io/blog/pharousermanagement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My task was to extend an address book located on this blog: &lt;a href=&#34;http://magaloma.blogspot.de/2011/01/pharo-gui-with-polymorph.html&#34;&gt;http://magaloma.blogspot.de/2011/01/pharo-gui-with-polymorph.html&lt;/a&gt;. It featured adding, editing, and deleting a contact and only had two fields: first name and last name. I extended the applicatino by adding an email field after loading the program in Pharo 4.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Gofer it
 squeaksource: &#39;Pharocasts&#39;;
 package: &#39;ContactManager&#39;;
 load.
 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt;, in the contact class, I added an instance variable called email. After that, I could add methods in the &lt;em&gt;accessing&lt;/em&gt; protocol that returns the email and also add the email to be printed in the printOn method in the &lt;em&gt;printing&lt;/em&gt; protocol. Last, I amended &lt;code&gt;ContactListEditor&amp;gt;&amp;gt;#contacts&lt;/code&gt; to include actually printing out the email address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://puu.sh/mcywp/bea6834b21.png&#34; alt=&#34;email&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smalltalk is a reflective language and was designed for constructionist learning, a method designed to reconstruct a learner&amp;rsquo;s knowledge rather to transmit new knowledge. In my short experience using Pharo Smalltalk, I found it quite different primarily due to the enivironment it is being run in but also due to the syntax. I never coded in any language that needed to be run in its own image and found it to be quite odd. Pharo smalltalk&amp;rsquo;s syntax also seems very different from the syntax I am used to seeing. I hope to continue doing smalltalk tasks for Google Code-in and explore smalltalk further even after GCI.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>